Hello! Welcome to
another episode of Bug Bounty Reports Explained.
Today, I will show you how Frans Rosén
broke shared Apple Shortcuts
by exploiting improper
access control bug.
If you stay until the end,
you will also see why he got the bounty of $28,000
despite violating Apple bug bounty rules.
Link to the original report is in the description.
Enjoy!
Unlike other tools out there,
Detectify that is both asset discovery by,
for example, crawling your DNS,
and then it also does vulnerability scanning.
Of course, it can do simple things from OWASP top 10
like CORS misconfiguration or check vulnerable versions,
but the cool part is
they are working
with a private community of ethical hackers
who submit payloads or POCs with automate
web vulnerabilities.
After the review,
Detectify runs the attack on all their customers
and every time there is a hit,
the hacker gets a bounty.
So if you are a defender
and you want to protect your apps,
check out free 2 week trial at
detectify.com/bbre
And, remember go hack yourself.
Apple shortcuts
is a platform that allows you automating stuff
on your iPhone
For example, I use it for my morning automation
where it asks me for my weight,
if I ate supplements and so on.
And then communicates with API to insert data
into spreadsheets or mark to those tasks as done.
In my case, it's mostly iPhone to server communication,
but there are tons of interactions that
can be done between different apps on your phone.
And your shortcuts are start using Apple's CloudKit.
It's a cloud database storage that allows many apps
to save the user's data and authenticate
directly from the phone using apple single sign on.
And this data is stored inside containers,
Apple shortcuts used COM.APPLE.SHORTCUTS container
Inside, you have three different databases.
Private to which only the owner has access.
Shared which can be, well... shared with other users.
and Public to which everyone has access.
Normally,
your shortcuts are stored in the Private database
and you must authenticate as yourself
to access them.
Shortcuts can be very complex.
To make things easier,
you don't need to create all of them from scratch.
There is a whole ecosystem of sharing them.
You can find and use shortcuts created by
others on websites like RoutineHub.
Some of them include thousands of steps
maybe you would think that
Shared cloud database
sounds like a perfect fit for that,
but apparently it wasn't.
When you want to share your shortcut
a new record with type
shared shortcut is created in the public database,
it gets a GUID
and a link
which you can use to send it to other people.
You must know that this
is the third vulnerability that Frans found
and described in the blog post.
Others allowed modifying the data on iCrowd website and
deleting articles from Apple news.
So he had some ideas on how to work with CloudKit.
It's important,
because it's not always easy
to query the CloudKit database.
For example, the Notes app
would communicate with the CloudKit using a request
that looks like this:
While the request from the developer portal
looked more like this:
Apple Shortcuts on the other hand talked to
gateway.icloud.com
Using protobuf messages
which made it significantly harder to fiddle.
However, it was possible to connect
to the shortcuts container
by talking to the endpoint originally used
by the developer portal.
What you needed to do is modifying the container name
in the request.
This way, it was possible
to communicate with the shortcuts container
using simple JSON bodies.
The obvious and very impact attacks that come to mind
are adding modifying or deleting other users' shortcuts.
However, access control
was properly enforced on all those scenarios.
And one more thing you need to know
about CloudKit are zones.
Public and shared databases can only use
the default zone.
But in private one, you can create
new zones to group related objects together.
At least, that's what the documentation says.
But turned out
that the public database in shortcuts container,
did use more than that.
It also had metadata_zone.
It was even possible to add new zones to the database,
but there was no impact to this
as your zone wouldn't be used by anyone.
You could also delete the zone you created,
but only when authenticated as the same user.
It hinted that access control is
properly enforced on those zones.
But anyway, Frans wanted to test if it was
also possible to delete the metadata_zone.
There was no other way to test this,
other than trying to delete it.
But he got an error saying
user updates to system zones are not allowed
which was the next hint
that access control is properly enforced here.
But anyway, he tried to delete the _defaultZone as well.
It was the last
idea he had for testing this functionality.
And this time,
it worked...
or it didn't?!
Listing zones still returned the _defaultZone
like nothing was changed.
So he started looking into other functionalities,
but he realized that
one of his shared shortcuts was gone...
So did the shortcut gallery...
Shortcut sharing website as well...
Turned out that all of the short shortcuts were deleted.
Only those shared after the deletion were working.
My guess is that the new _defaultZone was created just
after the previous one was deleted.
Hence, it was present in the zone listing response.
It was that much more problematic,
because Apple couldn't just
restore shortcuts from that moment,
because the new ones would be then removed.
They had to merge the old ones with the new ones,
which took a few days.
Obviously, this is something you never want to see
when bughunting.
Frans wrote an email to Apple a few minutes later
explaining what happened.
Later, he followed up
clarifying the steps he took
to prevent any service interruption,
and try to explain how limited he was
to confirm if the deletion call had worked or not.
Thanks to that,
he got the bounty of $28,000 for this vulnerability.
This shows that
even if you go a little too far with your testing,
you can still get a reward
if you justify that you did what you could
to avoid that.
Thank you for watching this episode!
I wish your bugs will never cause such problems.
If you enjoyed this video,
you may also like this one
about 50k remote code execution
in Apple Bug Bounty Program.
For now, thank you for watching and goodbye!